Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and it's the holiday season, Marco.
我是Catherine，现在是假期季节，Marco。
People are eating large meals with their families and I think oftentimes when you cook a lot
人们和家人一起吃大餐，我觉得很多时候当你做很多
of food, you have something extra at the end.
食物时，最后总会剩下一些。
What do we call that?
我们管那叫什么？
That's right.
没错。
Today we're going to talk about leftovers.
今天我们要聊聊剩菜。
That's the extra food after your meal that you eat later, maybe the next day.
就是饭后剩下的食物，你之后会吃，可能第二天。
Exactly.
没错。
So, you know, during Christmas or during some holidays, we cook so much food that obviously
所以，你知道，在圣诞节或一些假期期间，我们做太多食物，显然
we can't eat it all.
我们吃不完。
So we put it back in the refrigerator and then we eat it later.
所以我们把它放回冰箱，然后之后吃。
So those are called leftovers.
所以那些就叫剩菜。
All right.
好的。
So let's listen to this dialogue about leftovers and we'll be back in a moment to discuss what's
那么我们来听一段关于剩菜的对话，稍后我们会回来讨论
happening in the dialogue.
对话里发生了什么。
What's for dinner?
晚饭吃什么？
Leftovers.
剩菜。
What?
什么？
Leftovers of what and from when?
什么剩菜，从什么时候的？
From last night.
从昨晚的。
I took the leftover turkey, mixed it with some diced peppers and onions, add a little
我把剩下的火鸡拿出来，和切碎的青椒、洋葱混在一起，加一点
bit of mayonnaise and made some sandwiches.
蛋黄酱，做了些三明治。
Isn't that dangerous though?
但那不是很危险吗？
I mean, bacteria and germs reproducing on food that was left out or reheated.
我是说，细菌和病菌在放着的或重新加热的食物上繁殖。
Well, I didn't leave the turkey out at room temperature for more than an hour and I refrigerated
嗯，我没有把火鸡在室温下放超过一小时，而且我们吃完后
soon after we finished eating.
很快就冷藏了。
Also when reheating, I put it in the oven for 15 minutes at 100 degrees Celsius.
还有重新加热时，我把它放进烤箱，100摄氏度烤了15分钟。
Well, okay.
好吧。
I'm just afraid of getting food poisoning.
我只是怕食物中毒。
Don't worry about it.
别担心。
Making a new meal out of leftovers is almost an art.
用剩菜做新菜几乎是一门艺术。
Not only do you save money, but you also get to be creative and have something different
你不仅省钱，还能发挥创意，吃到不一样
to eat.
的东西。
All right.
好的。
So a lot of vocab there.
所以那里有很多词汇。
Let's take a look at it in Language Takeaway.
我们来看看语言要点部分。
Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
All right.
好的。
So Marco, there's one cooking term really in this dialogue that is, it's a little bit
所以Marco，这段对话里有一个烹饪术语，它有点
different from the others.
与众不同。
So let's start with that.
我们就从那个开始吧。
It's diced.
是“切碎的”。
That's right.
没错。
We were talking about taking some peppers or diced peppers.
我们刚才在说拿一些青椒或切碎的青椒。
So when you dice a vegetable or anything that you're cooking, basically you're making little
所以当你切碎蔬菜或任何你正在烹饪的东西时，基本上就是切成小块，
pieces, little squares almost.
几乎是小方块。
That's right.
没错。
So you can cut something many different ways.
所以你可以用很多不同方式切东西。
You can cut big pieces and small pieces, but diced peppers, diced is a specific way to
你可以切大块和小块，但切碎的青椒，“切碎”是一种特定的方式，
cut something in small, like you say, small squares.
像你说的，切成小方块。
And so in recipes, you will often see this instruction, dice the peppers, or in this
所以在食谱里，你经常会看到这个指示，切碎青椒，或者在这个
case, the peppers are diced.
例子里，青椒是切碎的。
That's right.
没错。
All right.
好的。
So we took some turkey, mix it with diced peppers and a lot of things.
所以我们拿了一些火鸡，和切碎的青椒以及很多东西混在一起。
And the roommate was a little bit concerned about bacteria and germs.
而室友有点担心细菌和病菌。
All right.
好的。
So bacteria and germs, these sound like very scientific words.
所以细菌和病菌，这些听起来很科学。
Bacteria is something that grows on, well, everything really.
细菌是生长在……嗯，几乎所有东西上的东西。
But if you leave food out, for example, it gets bacteria or germs are things that can
但如果你把食物放着，比如，它就会滋生细菌，或者病菌是能让你
make you sick.
生病的东西。
That's right.
没错。
So we need to avoid these things in the kitchen because they make us unhealthy.
所以我们在厨房里要避免这些东西，因为它们让我们不健康。
And that's why we wash our hands and things like that.
这就是为什么我们要洗手之类的。
But when you have food that's left out, the risk is what, Marco?
但当你把食物放着时，风险是什么，Marco？
Is that you get bacteria or germs on it.
就是食物上会滋生细菌或病菌。
Yeah.
是的。
So it's dangerous, especially with meat.
所以很危险，尤其是肉类。
If you leave it out, it's very, very dangerous because you can get some bacteria that will
如果你把它放着，非常非常危险，因为你会得到一些让你
make you sick.
生病的细菌。
And the reason why we're a little bit concerned, especially with meats, is if you leave it
我们有点担心的原因，尤其是肉类，是如果你在烹饪后把它
out after cooking it at room temperature.
放在室温下。
All right.
好的。
So room temperature is the temperature of a normal room.
所以室温就是一个普通房间的温度。
Maybe it's 65 degrees or what's 25 degrees Celsius.
可能是65华氏度或25摄氏度。
It's the temperature of the inside of a room.
就是房间内部的温度。
And so it's not cold, it's not hot, it's just normal.
所以不冷也不热，就是正常温度。
And when we leave food out, especially meat, like you're saying, we have to be careful.
当我们把食物放着时，尤其是像你说的肉类，我们必须小心。
You can't leave it out for very long if it's something like eggs or milk or what we call
如果是像鸡蛋、牛奶或者我们所说的易腐食品，你不能把它放太久。
perishables.
易腐食品。
That's right.
没错。
So actually, here comes the other two words that are a little bit of a contrast.
所以实际上，这里又来了两个有点对比的词。
We're going to talk about food that is reheated or refrigerated.
我们要讨论的是重新加热或冷藏的食物。
All right.
好的。
So the roommate is explaining, don't worry, we have done these things to this food so
所以室友在解释，别担心，我们对这些食物做了处理，所以
it's safe.
是安全的。
So one thing you can do to food to make it safe to kill germs is to reheat it.
所以让食物安全、杀死细菌的一种方法就是重新加热。
That means, well, you know the word heated, right?
这意味着，嗯，你知道“加热”这个词，对吧？
It's to make something hot.
就是让某物变热。
How is that different from reheated?
那和“重新加热”有什么不同？
Well, because you cooked it already, so it was warm.
嗯，因为你已经煮过了，所以它本来是热的。
Now it went a little bit cold because it's at room temperature.
现在因为放在室温下，变得有点凉了。
So in order to make sure that it's safe to eat and you kill that bacteria, you reheat
所以为了确保它安全可吃并杀死细菌，你重新加热
it so you kind of cook it again a little bit.
它，相当于再煮一下。
Yeah, you cook it again.
是的，再煮一次。
So with leftovers, we often have to reheat things because they were hot, then they were
所以对于剩菜，我们经常需要重新加热，因为它们本来是热的，然后变凉了，现在我们又想让它们变热。
cold and now we want them hot again.
没错。
That's right.
所以我们重新加热它们。
So we reheat them.
相反的做法是冷藏。
The opposite of that would be refrigerate.
对，这才是你应该做的。
Right, and this is what you should do.
如果你把某物放进冰箱，你做的动作，动词就是
If you take something and put it in the refrigerator, what you are doing, the verb, the action is
冷藏它。
to refrigerate it.
没错。
That's right.
所以冷藏某物意味着让它变冷。
So to refrigerate something means to make it cold.
你知道，有些重要的东西我们需要冷藏。
You know, there are important things that we refrigerate.
我们冷藏鸡蛋、牛奶、黄油。
We refrigerate eggs, we refrigerate milk, we refrigerate butter.
这些如果不冷藏，可能会让我们生病。
These are things that can make us sick if we don't make them cold.
完全正确。
Exactly.
所以这就是这两个词。
So those are the two words.
现在显然，它们有点不同，因为前缀“re-”表示再次做，而“冷藏”只是让它变冷。
Now obviously, it's a little bit different because the prefix to reheat means to do it
是的。
again while to refrigerate means you're just making it cold.
嗯，它们是重要的术语，而且我们还有形容词形式。
Yeah.
这是“重新加热过的”或“冷藏过的”。
Well, they're important terms and again, we also have the adjectives.
但还有几个非常重要的短语，让我们听听
This is reheated or refrigerated.
流利度构建器里的内容。
But there are another couple of phrases that are really important so let's take a listen
流利度构建器。
to those in Fluency Builder.
好的，我们要看的第一个短语是其中一个室友说，
Fluency Builder.
嘿，晚饭吃什么？
All right, so the first phrase we're going to take a look at is when one of the roommates
晚饭吃什么？
says, hey, what's for dinner?
好的，这是一个非常非常标准的短语。
What's for dinner?
这是你在家里、和朋友在一起时会听到的。
All right, this is a very, very standard phrase.
通常是在有人做晚饭时我们会说的话。
This is something you'll hear at home, you'll hear with your friends.
没错。
It's usually something we say that when someone is cooking food for dinner.
我们在问：我们晚饭要吃什么？
That's right.
妈妈，晚饭吃什么？
We're asking what are we going to eat for dinner?
没错。
Mom, what's for dinner?
我以前每天放学回家都会这么说。
Exactly.
嗯，显然，你不想说那么长的句子。
I used to say that every single day when I came home from school.
我们今晚要吃什么？
Well, obviously, you don't want to say the long phrase.
所以你就简单说：晚饭吃什么？
What are we going to have for dinner tonight?
晚饭吃什么？
So you just say, what's for dinner?
然后答案可能是千层面或火鸡三明治。
What's for dinner?
对，没错。
And then the answer would be lasagna or turkey sandwiches.
当他们开始谈论剩火鸡时，他有点担心，就像我们
Right, exactly.
说的细菌和病菌，因为通常食物放久了就会这样。
Now when they started talking about the leftover turkey, he was a little bit concerned as we
好的，所以这里的动词是“leave out”，把某物放在外面。
said about bacteria and germs because it usually happens that you get this on food that was
意思是把某物放在室温下。
left out.
所以马可，你和我正在吃火鸡，今天是感恩节，我们开始喝咖啡
All right, so the verb here is to leave out, to leave something out.
吃甜点，火鸡还在房间里，处于室温。
It means to leave something or put something at room temperature.
我们没有冷藏它。
So Marco, you and I are eating turkey, it's Thanksgiving, and we start to have coffee
那就意味着它被放在外面了。
and dessert and the turkey is still in the room, at room temperature.
它被放在外面多久了？
We did not refrigerate it.
嗯，大概两个小时。
That means it was left out.
意思是它不在冰箱里。
How long was it left out?
没错。
Well, maybe two hours.
这就是它的意思。
That means so it's not in a refrigerator.
所以也许你去睡觉了，把火鸡放在外面。
That's right.
它可能还在桌子上，处于室温。
That's exactly what it means.
哦不，如果放外面12个小时，我们就不能吃了。
So maybe you go to sleep and you left the turkey out.
没错。
It's still on the table maybe at room temperature.
好的，所以把食物放在外面不好。
Oh no, we can't eat it if we left it out for like 12 hours.
现在如果你吃了放太久的东西，可能会
Exactly.
食物中毒。
All right, so it's not good to leave food out.
这很严重，你在做饭时应该非常小心。
And now what happens is if you do eat food that was left out for too long, you could
没错。
get food poisoning.
所以如果你吃了放太久的东西，可能会
Now this is very serious and it's something that you should be very careful about when
食物中毒。
you're cooking.
这很严重，你在做饭时应该非常小心。
Food poisoning is getting sick from your food.
食物中毒是指吃了食物后生病。
There are different kinds of food poisoning, but usually it makes you throw up, it makes
食物中毒有多种类型，但通常会导致呕吐，
your stomach hurt, it's quite painful.
胃痛，非常痛苦。
That's right.
没错。
And this is why we say you should wash your hands before you cook.
这就是为什么我们说做饭前要洗手。
You should make sure that you refrigerate meat because you want to avoid food poisoning.
你应该确保把肉冷藏起来，因为要避免食物中毒。
That's right.
没错。
And it comes from the noun poison, a poison, which is something that is harmful for your
这个词来自名词 poison，即毒药，是对身体有害的东西。
body.
身体。
That's right.
没错。
There are many different kinds of poison, but food poisoning means becoming sick, your
毒药有很多种，但食物中毒是指生病，
body getting sick after you eat something bad.
吃了变质食物后身体不适。
That's right.
没错。
All right.
好了。
So with all this stuff here, we can review everything one last time.
那么，有了这些内容，我们可以最后复习一遍。
What's for dinner?
晚饭吃什么？
Leftovers.
剩菜。
What?
什么？
Leftovers of what and from when?
什么剩菜，从什么时候的？
From last night.
昨晚的。
I took the leftover turkey, mixed it with some diced peppers and onions, add a little
我把剩下的火鸡切碎，和切好的青椒、洋葱混在一起，加了一点
bit of mayonnaise and made some sandwiches.
蛋黄酱，做了些三明治。
Isn't that dangerous though?
那样做不会很危险吗？
I mean, bacteria and germs reproducing on food that was left out or reheated.
我是说，细菌和微生物在放凉或重新加热的食物上繁殖。
Well I didn't leave the turkey at a room temperature for more than an hour and I refrigerated soon
嗯，我没有把火鸡在室温下放超过一小时，而且吃完后很快就
after we finished eating.
放进冰箱了。
Also when reheating, I put it in the oven for 15 minutes at 100 degrees Celsius.
另外，重新加热时，我把它放在烤箱里，用100摄氏度烤了15分钟。
Well, okay.
好吧，那还行。
I'm just afraid of getting food poisoning.
我只是怕食物中毒。
Don't worry about it.
别担心。
Making a new meal out of leftovers is almost an art.
用剩菜做新菜几乎是一门艺术。
Not only do you save money, but you also get to be creative and have something different
不仅省钱，还能发挥创意，吃到不一样的东西。
to eat.
吃。
All right, so this is actually good advice about leftovers, about having something to
好吧，这确实是关于剩菜的好建议，关于有东西
eat.
吃。
But at the same time, I don't know how many people actually are very careful with these
但与此同时，我不知道有多少人真的对这些事情
things.
很小心。
For example, pizza.
比如披萨。
Sometimes you leave pizza out on the table all night and the next morning you have some
有时候你把披萨放在桌上过夜，第二天早上还能吃一些
pizza.
披萨。
I always refrigerate my pizza.
我总是把披萨放冰箱里。
I know people who leave their pizza out and then eat it, but there's cheese and sausage
我知道有人把披萨放外面然后接着吃，但那可是奶酪和香肠啊。
and you want to refrigerate that stuff.
而且你想冷藏那些东西。
So I always wrap it in plastic and put it on a plate in the fridge.
所以我总是用保鲜膜包好，放在冰箱里的盘子上。
Oh, okay.
哦，好吧。
You wrap it in plastic.
你用塑料把它包起来。
Well, because in the refrigerator there's also germs, so you need to make sure you cover
嗯，因为冰箱里也有细菌，所以你得确保盖好。
your food.
你的食物。
Right, right, right.
对，对，对。
What about, have you ever had a bad case of food poisoning because of having leftovers?
那你有过因为吃剩菜而食物中毒的糟糕经历吗？
No.
不。
I've had food poisoning, but not because of leftovers.
我食物中毒过，但不是因为剩菜。
Because as I said before, I wrap things, I put them in the refrigerator.
就像我之前说的，我会把东西包好，然后放进冰箱。
I'm very careful because I don't want to get sick or I don't want to get other people sick.
我非常小心，因为我不想生病，也不想让别人生病。
But Thanksgiving or Christmas, you have to give food to many other people.
但是感恩节或圣诞节，你得给很多人准备食物。
I don't want to make anyone sick.
我不想让任何人吃坏肚子。
And actually, you can get food poisoning not only from leftovers, but from maybe food that
实际上，你不仅可能因为剩菜而食物中毒，也可能因为某些食物本身。
maybe was expired.
可能过期了。
Sometimes cheese maybe can be expired, you didn't realize it, and you get food poisoning.
有时候奶酪可能过期了，你没注意到，然后就会食物中毒。
Or from people who are cooking with things that are not clean.
或者是因为人们用不干净的东西做饭。
So you have something that's not clean or food that's not fresh and it makes you very
所以，如果你有东西不干净或者食物不新鲜，它会让你非常
sick.
生病。
So it's not good for your health.
所以这对你的健康不好。
So you have to be careful.
所以你必须小心。
That's right.
没错。
So it's an interesting thing, especially with, like I said, so many holidays where you cook
所以这挺有意思的，尤其是像我说的，那么多节日里你做了
so much food that people have a lot of leftovers.
太多食物，人们会有很多剩菜。
And not only that, but even at restaurants, maybe you order too much, so you have leftovers
不仅如此，甚至在餐馆里，你可能点得太多，所以有剩菜
you want to take home to your dog or to have later.
想带回家给狗吃或者以后吃。
I love leftovers.
我喜欢剩菜。
Let us know, do you have leftovers in your country?
告诉我们，你们国家有剩菜吗？
Are there things that you should and shouldn't do when cooking?
做饭时有什么该做和不该做的事吗？
Let us know.
告诉我们吧。
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
我们的网站是EnglishPod.com。
All right, we'll see you guys there.
好了，我们那里见。
Bye for now.
再见。